Simon Fraser Teachers' Union fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Simon Fraser Teachers' Union fonds
1967 - 1968
F-118
Q106642994
13 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Simon Fraser Teachers' Union
The Simon Fraser Teachers' Union held its organizational meeting and first general meeting on July 27, 1967. Its membership consisted of faculty members who felt that the Simon Fraser University Faculty Association (SFUFA) was not representing their interests. The SFTU remained active until 1968, when it integrated into the SFUFA after that body called for the resignation of SFU's president, Patrick Duncan McTaggart-Cowan.
The SFTU was formed, in part, as a reaction to perceived inadequacies with the SFUFA due to its close association with university administration. The SFTU was distinct from the SFUFA because it excluded from its membership the President, administrators, heads, librarians and teaching assistants. The SFTU was designed to deal solely with the problems of faculty members, and to advocate on their behalf
The Teachers' Union's stated aims were as follows:
to promote, establish, and maintain the highest academic standards among the members of the full-time teaching faculty at Simon Fraser University; to concern itself with the welfare of its membership specifically in the areas of academic freedom, tenure, promotions, dismissal and renewal procedures, and in general to adopt the methods of collective bargaining in furthering the vital interests of its membership; to ensure that the university adheres to democratic principles and procedures in the relations that are established between students, teaching assistants, faculty, administration, and all other members of the academic community; to provide ways and means of furthering the interests of faculty not available through other teacher associations (e.g. Faculty Association, CAUT), due to the limited effectiveness imposed upon such associations by their structure, and, by the exclusion of heads of departments and other administrative personnel, to minimize conflicts of interest that militate against the best interests of the faculty.
The Simon Fraser Teachers' Union executive, consisting of a president, vice-president, secretary, treasurer, corresponding secretary, and four directors managed the business of the union. The STU was the first union of university professors in Canada, although it did not receive certification under the existing labour code.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on its provenance.
The fonds consists of records created, received and collected by the Simon Fraser Teachers' Union in carrying out its stated objectives. Includes the union's constitution, draft amendments to the constitution, correspondence, membership applications and cards, minutes, agenda, reports, financial records, memoranda, and newspaper clippings.
The materials were arranged by the Archivist.
Labour
Unknown.
All accessions have been processed as of September 2002. No further accruals are expected.
Please consult the inventory for the Simon Fraser University Faculty Association fonds, F-79, the Faculty Council fonds, F-112, and the Joint Faculty fonds, F-113.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
A file list is available.
- Constitution, 1967; F-118-0-0-0-1 (Archival box - small 118-1)
  published
  Textual records
  Pending review
- Draft amendments to Constitution, 1967 - 1968; F-118-0-0-0-2 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Correspondence - Constitution, 1967; F-118-0-0-0-3 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Informational Notices - Formation of Union, 1967 - 1968; F-118-0-0-0-4 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Applications for membership and membership cards, 1967; F-118-0-0-0-5 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Executive nomination ballot, 1967; F-118-0-0-0-6 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Membership drive notes, 1967 - 1968; F-118-0-0-0-7 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Minutes and agenda, 1967; F-118-0-0-0-8 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Reports to faculty; SFTU News; Union position papers, 1967 - 1968; F-118-0-0-0-9 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Bank statements and finance notes, 1967 - 1968; F-118-0-0-0-10 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Faculty Association memoranda, 1967 - 1968; F-118-0-0-0-11 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Correspondence - affiliation, 1967; F-118-0-0-0-12 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Union President's incoming correspondence, 1967 - 1968; F-118-0-0-0-13 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Union President's outgoing correspondence to University President, 1967 - 1968; F-118-0-0-0-14 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Memoranda from University President, 1967 - 1968; F-118-0-0-0-15 (Archival box - small 118-1)
- Newspaper clippings - Teachers' Union, 1967 - 1968; F-118-0-0-0-16 (Archival box - small 118-1)